[Music]
welcome to the final part of the
miniseries with a psychedelic
philosopher of mine Peter shuts dead H
if you found the series interesting so
far please share it around subscribe to
the mailing list at boys club comm and
leave a review on the platform you use
to listen let's get into
[Music]
so fitti you were just mentioning the
link between Whitehead and epigenetics
yes so in terms of evolution and a way
of thinking about evolution in terms of
you know T biology or whatever white had
had more than actual influence on the
evolution of science than people realize
because epigenetics which used to be
heresy in science it's the notion that
the expression of genes is caused by the
environment rather than former former
genes so in other words the way you
behave has an effect upon the expression
of you at not only your genes but the
genes of your offspring and even a
generation fast forward yep
so epigenetics some people say it's a
return to Lamarck you know Lamarque came
up with theory evolution before darwin
which said believed in them soft
inheritance as it was known so if you
acted in a certain way that behavior
would somehow be taken after by your
children and grandchildren people didn't
believe it but actually now with
epigenetics in a way that's a form of
Lamarckism because yeah the environment
does affect the genes of one's offspring
yeah
epigenetics now has been you know
established scientific field for last 15
years or so but it was created really by
someone called CH Waddington the
biologists geneticists an epigenetic
cyst and he in his autobiography he
explicitly said that he was a whitehead
ian and he was kind of secretly bring
Whitehead in metaphysics into his
hypotheses and by doing that I mean
there's there's a tract for example in
modes of thought where Whitehead says
you know our idea of the gene is an
abstraction because it completely
abstract from its environment what
really goes gene is part and parcel of
its environment its cell and self and
the self the organ the organ the body
the body the the actual environment
around us all of this is part of one
interacting process so to just delineate
the gene it's like delineating the atom
you know but rather as we know now the
atom is part and parcel of its
environment and it can be translated to
energy but the same same as with the
atom so with the gene and so even the
1930s Whitehead was talking about how
a form of sort of pure neo-darwinian
etics
can't be right and Waddington tested for
this and as a result of that we have
epigenetics today and of course
epigenetics we know as part of must be
crucial part of evolution because it is
about the expression of genes that means
that one's behavior influences evolution
it's not all about mutation sexual
selection natural selection right and
even more than that something that
Thomas Nagel philosopher Thomas Nagel
spoken about recently it's this notion
that if you reject epiphenomenalism the
view that as we said mentality has no
effect on the body or the environment
and no effect upon later mentality
either if you reject epiphenomenalism so
in other words you believe that the
mental has an effect upon the body as
most people actually believe you know if
you desire something it will actually
cause your body to move and I think you
have to accept mental causation
otherwise for example reason has no
purpose and as popper said if you well
Papa said that epiphenomenalism was
anti-darwinian or anti evolutionary
because we would not have evolved not
only humans but all you know mammals and
so on we would not have evolved
mentality if it did absolutely nothing
if it had no purpose for stijl organs
they don't have perhaps Knab but they
did have a purpose in the past but with
epi flawless and mentality never had a
purpose and doesn't have a purpose and
unless it's sustained in this primary
aspect of our reality of our lives yeah
so if you if you're an evolutionist you
should leave mental causation now here's
the interesting ramification of that
that Nagel brings out what Papa didn't
if you believe in mental causation then
you have to accept that mental causality
in other words thinking must have had a
profound effect upon evolution you know
the physical evolution of bodies so
through Whitehead and Magel and poplar
and so on although I think evolution is
of course true is a true process I think
we only have again an abstraction of it
I think we'll there's so much more to
learn about it epigenetics is the first
step in realizing that mental causation
is a real force not necessarily the same
thing as free will but our minds still
have an effect upon physical reality
right so you telling me Peter that these
Facebook mean pages are actually deeply
involved with
future evolution of humanity everything
plays its part oh yeah well I mean the
thing I mean look this you know you
might have even included in your summary
of your viewing on your webpage but that
this was a view that accords with a
union understanding of archetypes right
just in just in that well I mean if
mentality is involved in directly and in
affecting the course of evolution then
therefore so or our metaphysics which
you might take as on this kind of view
where the action is considered the most
real I mean metaphysics is ultimately
about informing the deepest substrata of
the cogs that turn will ultimately
become our actions however you
characterize how they filter up from
that deep level perhaps through the
unconscious and what have you and so
interacting with that foundational
source and interacting with whatever the
process of engaging with being is that
allows you to move between these realms
so to speak yeah I think we're in other
words we're uncovering other forms of
causality other than the known full
forces nature if the right Valco types
are real then of course they will have
an effect upon one's behavior and one's
character you know that's their purpose
really yeah absolutely that's evolution
itself yeah in fact if you don't believe
in mental causation you don't really
believe in psychology as a science
because it's just be reducible to
neurophysiology well absolutely i mean
it's it's isn't it isn't it so
interesting i this is a slightly
different question then it seems to me
if we just take our books on you an
approach where we have on the one hand
intellectualization roughly put in
Russells terms the scientific impulse
and on the other hand of bugs and we
have intuition roughly put on the raw
setting conception as the mystical
impulse we have these two sides so to
speak of man and well it seems that in
different disciplines in different areas
of life perhaps poetry as as versus
analytic philosophy you have an
identification with one rather than the
other in some sense do you think that
the the psychological disposition of an
individual just that temperament
essentially would influence the
discipline they end up philosopher might
end up pursuing and therefore an
ultimately prejudicing
his way of grounding himself in what he
thought was real yeah I mean it brings
to mind
neech and beyond Knievel where his as a
philosophers work is really just a
reflection of this character right
absolutely I believe that I mean if
you're predisposed towards children
you're much more likely to end up in
child care than building right or
philosophy or whatever of course you
know your character which i think is
sort of inborn mostly mostly when you
look at children like twins brought up
in the same household oh yeah yeah
totally I mean there's a lot of evidence
to show that character is innate to a
certain extent but erm
but of course you know vironment will
affect that so you know you might have a
bent towards science but if it's not an
offer in your country intent of course
you won't do it and you'll perhaps be
unhappy you know I think most people are
not happy with that content with their
vocations and that's brings a lot of
misery to reality mm-hmm and I think in
many cases people don't know what their
vocation is so I'm quite lucky to to
know that philosophy sort of makes me
happy I'm also sort of you know
artistically orientated to some extent I
mean that doesn't surprise me
so I I believe I am too although what I
am aiming at and I think almost by a
necessity if if you take yourself to be
artistically inclined but end up doing
philosophy what's what ends up happening
is if you sort of have to build your own
bridge to credibility fundamentally and
given that the analytic philosophical
institution let's just say it's built on
the rational intellect yeah without the
artistic element yeah I mean it's
interesting because in a way philosophy
is the bridge between science and art
isn't but analytic philosophy is much
more on the scientific side exactly
however to be a good analytic
philosopher like jaegwan Kim one of my
favorites philosopher mind one has to
have style and one's writing and that's
not yeah there's a craft so the greatest
analytic philosophers will still be
artists in that sense
Bertrand Russell even his early work was
like that yeah Bertrand Russell won the
greatest of all English writers I think
so you can't really avoid it
Whitehead said um style is the last
night acquisition of the educated mind
however I think yeah so the boring
analytic philosophers are the ones who
have got no artist
dick talent but you can go too far the
other direction as well and just sort of
get where you'll end up in poetry and
some people say that Nietzsche for
example was only a poet an art
philosopher the ideal really I think is
shopping Hauer he's he's right he's he's
you know the golden mean so he's got
these great analytical moves great
logical moves at the same time the turns
of phrase are beautiful and the
metaphors his great metaphors you know I
remain are sublime so so that's thing
that's the ultimate aim you know
Schopenhauer and writer that's the ideal
for the philosopher
just between poetry and science right so
I have one final thing especially
because we don't have too much long
longer together irrespective of this
recording and I don't know if I'll
include this one but part of the idea
that I'm using to try and tie together
that broad the main of thought I'm
trying to bring together in my
dissertation these conceptions of part
making and whole making where part
making here is broadly construed as
something like
the power
mence instrumental utility associated
with fixing the world and investigating
it with analysis and empirically and
what-have-you and on the other hand this
whole making which to put it in the
language of the conversation today would
be a sort of identification with or
Haigh sort of expressed it as as bearing
an effective relation to this source of
transcendent value something like that
where I guess the value accessible when
holding yourself properly to the mode of
intuition in the work Sounion sense it's
what enables the creative evolution of
Birks and in some sense the creative
metaphysics that essentially it's bound
to creating a or Ultima and maybe
aligning itself with or creating itself
with or holistically devising a schema
for action a set of hierarchically
arranged goals even though you might not
be consciously aware of exactly what
they are
so in somehow it's it's it's going
outside of the established structure
where part making ostensibly only works
within and already imagined whole to
sort of echo it out the whole making is
what occurs when the explorer goes out
into the unknown right and so I'm trying
to use this notions of part making and
hole making to sort of tie together the
utility of both worlds because I want to
save the utility obviously of science
and save how accurately it's able to
come to describe reality at certain
levels well I recommend the book where
William James called a pluralistic
universe but he talks about the values
of both intellect and intuition and he
uses three main thinkers in that book
widget which are Hegel Fechner and James
and he uses himself sorry Hegel feculent
Berg's on me and end himself professor
but he contrasts in like Burke Saunders
intellect and intuition and how a full
understanding reality requires this
intuition along Burke's only Alliance
but intellects yeah his cuts up reality
in two parts so that we can deal with it
you know so I mean language itself you
know every word at least every
we use is a cutting reality into that
concepts you know whereas in reality of
course far transcends that words you
know like apple or tree or something
like this and you know to talk about its
entire evolution and its relation to
everything else its gravity you know
whatever so when we communicate we have
to use abstractions but the danger is
verification you know like thinking now
the abstraction the concept is the
sufficient totality and it's very you
know Pete that's why people are prone to
materialism generally because you know
everything's cut up into little parts
atomism and as ideal and we can express
those ration ship between those parts
are calling to these forces that we've
derived from observing regular
occurrences and so on but it's real
danger because yeah it's artificial
cutouts and when you realize that then
you enter metaphysics I think
immediately but you know that's like a
whole book by them so it'd be hard to
say more Whitehead again bugs whiteheads
great I mean he calls at the fallacy of
misplaced concreteness very common and
the fallacy of simple location for an
atom or gene for example there's a lot
to look into there but yeah process
philosophies is the complete antithesis
of that compartmentalizing
intellectuality here process philosophy
may as well sign off again name is very
much thank you Tim
big thanks to PETA for joining me for
these conversations I really look
forward to speaking to him again later
this year but at the end there we
touched on the dynamic between the
intellects and intuition in my work
aligned with the notions of part making
and home making which also seek to find
the modes of analysis and mysticism into
a sensical and mutually supportive
knowledge seeking process I would say
the characterization I gave of part
Mason homemaking in this recording were
definitely at an earlier stage of
development and I definitely give a
slightly different initial description
now I hope to publish this work in some
form later this year but if you're
interested to speak to me about it do
reach out you can reach me on the voice
Club Facebook page on Twitter or at Tim
at VoIP calm also if you're in Melbourne
Australia from time to time and want to
get involved in some discussion forums
reach out to me and we'll make that
happen
finally if you find this podcast
interesting don't hesitate to share it
and support it by signing up to the
mailing list at boys club comm and by
leaving a review on a platform like
iTunes or wherever you listen to it to
hear more from Peter you can visit his
website at philosophy you like his
facebook page at ontology sticks
so there's a lot more coming this year
but until then have a beautiful bloody
life
[Music]